Hello everyone and welcome to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
My name is Catherine and today we
have an intermediate level lesson for you.
It's kind of about cars, right?
That's right. So today we
are taking our car to the
mechanic and we're just going to check
things and make sure that our car is okay.
All right, so we're going to learn a lot
of really great words that have to do with
cars and what happens when cars break down.
So let's listen to our dialogue.
Welcome to Elzgarage.
What seems to be the problem?
No problem at all. I
am taking a long road
trip and I want to make
sure my car is in good
mechanical condition. Very wise decision.
When was the last time you had a tune up?
Not that long ago. I think
it was four months ago.
We usually recommend
that you bring
your car in every 5,000 kilometers. Why?
I mean, what exactly do you do to a car?
You need to check it so often.
First of all, we change
the motor oil and oil filter.
If you don't do this,
it can cause your
engine to wear faster
and that means you would
probably have to change the pistons
and intake valves. I see. What else?
We also check your
spark plugs, fuel filter
and other oil levels
such as hydraulic fluid.
We also check the clutch and brakes to
determine when you will need new ones.
Okay, well, when
you put it that way, it
doesn't seem like a
waste of time and money.
Trust me. Regular two nuts will keep your
car running smoothly and avoid breakdowns.
Alright, we're back. So
a very simple dialogue
with the mechanic
explaining to the client about
why you need to
take care of your car.
So he mentioned a couple
of very technical words in here.
Let's take a look at those
on language takeaway.
Language takeaway. The first phrase
we're looking at today is tune up.
So a tune up is a thing. It's a noun and
it's something you do to check your car.
So you take your car for a
tune up or you get a tune up.
Now this is for your car and this basically
means to check that your car is okay
and replace any very
easy things around the car.
So you don't normally get a
tune up when your car is broken.
You get a tune up
when your car is okay.
That's right. That's right.
So the mechanic explained some of the
things that you do when you get a tune up.
So for example, he said that
they change the motor oil.
Okay, so like it sounds,
motor oil is oil for your motor.
That's right. But there
are other kinds of oil as
well and the oil is
oftentimes put into the car.
And sometimes it falls
out and so there's what's
that thing that catches
the oil when it comes down?
Oil pan. In oil pan. So yes, as you
say, there are different types of oils.
Cooking oil is obviously
for cooking for you.
But motor oil is not for eating.
It's for your motor.
But we also have to change the oil filter.
Now this is an important part that
often gets mentioned at tune ups.
That's right. So the word filter
here, it's you have the verb two filter.
In this case, we also have a noun.
It's called a filter.
So what this device does, it
collects maybe dirt or rocks and
dust or anything that you
don't want to be in your engine.
And specifically maybe
if the oil is a little bit dirty.
Right. So an oil filter,
make sure that the oil
in your motor is not
going to harm your motor.
And we also have a couple of
interesting things like the fuel filter.
Now how is this
different from the oil filter?
It's a pretty much the same thing.
The only difference
is that this filter
specifically cleans the
gasoline in your car.
Okay. Similar object. After that,
that we have something very different.
These are spark plugs.
That's right. These are small little devices
that, as the name says, create a spark.
This is how your engine goes.
This is how your car moves.
You have a spark and then
everything starts running.
So spark plugs are actually
quite important, right?
That's right. So a spark is a like very
quick flash of light that comes out.
That's right. It's not a long light.
It's just a spark.
So maybe when I strike
a match or I use a lighter,
there's a spark and
that's what starts the fire.
That's right. That's exactly right.
So a spark plug. And now we
also check the oil levels of our car.
And that's a very important thing as well.
Yeah, that's right. So the oil level is
something that you test with a long stick.
And you put it into the engine.
The oil container and make
sure that there is enough oil.
Because if there's not enough oil,
you can have very serious car trouble.
That's right. So a
lot of technical or
mechanical things that
we're taking a look at.
Why don't we go back? Let's review
all these words and we'll be back in a bit.
Welcome to Al's Garage.
What seems to be the problem?
No problem at all. I am
taking a long road trip and I
want to make sure my car is
in good mechanical condition.
Very wise decision.
When was the last time you had a tune up?
Not that long ago.
I think it was four months ago.
We usually recommend that you
bring your car in every 5,000 km.
Why? I mean, what exactly do you do to
a car that you need to check it so often?
First of all, we change
the motor oil and oil filter.
If you don't do this, it can
cause your engine to wear faster.
And that means you would probably have
to change the pistons and intake valves.
I see. What else? We also
check your spark plugs, fuel
filter, and other oil levels,
such as hydraulic fluid.
We also check the clutch and brakes to
determine when you will need new ones.
Okay. Well, when
you put it that way, it
doesn't seem like a
waste of time and money.
Trust me. Regular tune-ups will keep your
car running smoothly and avoid breakdowns.
All right. We're back. So now we've
prepared three key phrases for you.
Let's take a look at those
now on Fluency Builder.
Fluency Builder. This
first phrase is something
that you often hear
in the service industry.
So anytime you're going to a
shop, or maybe in this case the
mechanic, the mechanical radio,
what seems to be the problem?
That's right. So this is a question. And
we're saying, what is wrong with your car?
Or maybe if you go to the doctor, the doctor
will say, what seems to be the problem?
What seems to be the problem? So
this means what's wrong with you?
Where do you have a problem?
This is a very, very
common phrase.
So remember this one. It
just means what's going on?
Why are you here? What can I help you with?
It's very polite though, right? It's
better than saying what's wrong with you.
No, yeah. You wouldn't want to say
what's wrong with you. That's very rude.
So what seems to be the problem is a
much more polite way of saying things.
Very good. And well,
the mechanic after
explaining everything,
he said that, you know,
doing all these things, changing the
filters will keep the car running smoothly.
Okay. So we're not talking about
running like a marathon here.
We're talking about using your car.
And so when we turn a car on, we
don't say that the car is operating really.
We say it's running. So
that means that it's in use
that I've turned the key
and the motor is running.
But if it's running well, we
say it's running smoothly.
So it's not having any problems.
Yeah. So if you turn
your car on and you hear
your engine, it sounds
very normal, no problems.
It's running smoothly. If it's going,
it's not running smoothly, that's right.
And obviously if you
don't take care of your car,
what may happen is you
may suffer a breakdown.
Okay. Remember this phrase as a
phrase because obviously things can break.
You know, I broke a glass. But as far as
cars are concerned, you say, you know,
a car breaks down or I
want to avoid breakdowns.
And so this is something that happens
when your car no longer works properly.
That's right.
So you say my car broke down yesterday.
And I had to call a friend
to pick me up because, you
know, when your car breaks
down, you can't go anywhere.
Right. You can't drive
it anymore. Very good.
So to break down now,
obviously if you get a flat tire,
that doesn't really mean
that your car broke down.
Now, a flat tire is a bit different. That
means that you have to replace the tire.
But when your car breaks down, it
means that something inside the car, like,
a piece of it, yeah, the transmission
or the spark plugs or the engine,
some part of it isn't working right.
And you have to get it fixed or replaced.
That's right. Okay. So a lot of
interesting things talking about cars here.
When we take a look at our dialogue again,
let's listen to it and be back in a bit.
Welcome to Elsgarage.
What seems to be the problem?
No problem at all. I am
taking a long road trip and I
want to make sure my car is
in good mechanical condition.
Very wise decision.
When was the last time you had a tune up?
Not that long ago.
I think it was four months ago.
We usually recommend that you
bring your car in every 5,000 kilometers.
Why? I mean, what exactly do you do to
a car that you need to check it so often?
First of all, we change
the motor oil and oil filter.
If you don't do this, it can
cause your engine to wear faster.
And that means you would probably have
to change the pistons and intake valves.
I see. What else?
We also check your
spark plugs, fuel filter,
and other oil levels,
such as hydraulic fluid.
We also check the clutch and brakes to
determine when you will need new ones.
Okay. Well, when
you put it that way, it
doesn't seem like a
waste of time and money.
Trust me. Regular tune-ups will keep your
car running smoothly and avoid breakdowns.
Okay, so talking about cars
and tune-ups now, when we go
to the mechanic, you saw that
he said welcome to Elsgarage.
So a mechanic shop is
usually called a garage.
That's right. And as you will know, a
garage is a place where we store cars.
So sometimes people
park their cars in the street.
But if you have a special place to
protect your car from the rain or the snow,
like a room for your
car, that's called a garage.
And this might be confusing, but a store,
like you say, for a mechanic is a garage.
Also, because there's a door that opens
up the same way, it opens up, not out.
Right, right. And you pull the car inside
and then the mechanic can fix the car.
And so I think that's why it's a garage.
There's room for many cars inside.
That's right. So you
take, or if your car is at the
mechanic shop, you would
say, oh, my car is at the garage.
It's getting fixed. Yeah, that's right.
But it's a little bit different from
the place where you would buy a car.
A place where you buy a
car is a car lot, L-O-T lot.
And that's a place
where they have many,
many cars outside,
like in a big parking lot.
That's what they call a lot. And you
can pick a car and buy it and test it.
But a place where
you fix a car, and that's
special, that's called a
garage or a repair shop.
Now, something that's
very interesting and very
common in places like
the States and Canada,
is that there are actually
used car lots where you can see
many cars that have, they're
used and they're trying to sell.
But obviously, in many other countries,
it's not very common to see a used car lot.
Well, I think in America,
people like to buy new cars, and
that means that every couple
of years they sell their old car.
But that car is still good.
You can still use a car from 2005.
In fact, when I had a car, it was from
1991. It was 16 years old at the time.
And so, you know, I could
still drive it. It was a good car,
and I think that as long as
you can drive it, you can sell it.
This is actually another
interesting thing about cars in
general, in places like this,
is that there are so many cars.
And as you say, people are often
buying new cars every year or trading
their cars every five years, let's say,
use cars are very, very inexpensive.
I mean, you can get a car
for like $500 sometimes.
That's right. And in a lot of
cases, it doesn't make sense to
buy a new car because it's going
to be less valuable in one day.
But a used car, as long as it doesn't
have any problems, like you don't
want to buy a car that has faulty,
you know, spark plugs or whatever.
As long as it runs
smoothly, I think that
it's a very good investment
to buy a used car.
Very good. So, it's
interesting because in many
countries, used cars are
actually not that much cheaper.
So why don't you come to our
website, www.EnglishPod.com.
Let us know if, you know, taking
your car to the mechanic is very
expensive or buying a used
car is still relatively expensive.
We hope to see you guys
there, and until next time, bye.
(upbeat music)